today we're going to talk about a very
interesting randomized control trial
that was published back in February of
2022 on intermittent fasting I'm Dr
Roger schw welcome to another true
Health Tuesdays now intermittent fasting
has been a interesting topic there's
been a number of papers that have been
published that have showed some efficacy
and also some other papers that have
showed lack of advocacy so it's been
been actually a bit of a controversial
topic but today we're going to look at a
head-to-head randomized control trial
which is the best type of evidence and
looking at seeing whether or not eating
in the morning and restricting eating to
just in the morning or the morning hours
or early versus restricting eating to
midday or later
afternoon so the name of this study is
randomized control trial for Tim
restricted eating and healthy volunteers
without obesity so this is the type of
person that we're looking for here and
specifically about and there are two
major different types
of interventions in this study one is
called
EF and that has to do with food intake
that is restricted to the early part of
the day so that would be calories
particularly ingested in the morning
time so bigger breakfasts much lighter
dinners things of that nature versus the
other type which is a midday trf or time
restricted feeding which is restricted
food to the middle of the day
okay so in this situation they conducted
a five week randomized control trial to
compare the effects of the two trf
regimens one where it is restricted to
the morning and one that is restricted
to the midday and these are in health
individuals without
obesity and there was one more group and
that was the control group so they took
90 participants and randomize them to 30
in the early Tim restricted feeding
group 30 in the midday Tim restricted
feeding group and then finally 30 in a
control group using a computer-based
random number
generator and as it turns out 82
participants completed the entire five
week trial that's pretty good in terms
of not having a lot of
Dropout and they wanted to see what
would happen to insulin resistance now
the researchers who assessed the
outcomes were blinded to the group
assignment but the participants and the
caregivers were not so it was not a
double blinded study but rather a single
blinded randomized control trial so
first of all there was no Adverse Events
reported during the trial so that was
good and sort of cutting to the chase
here what did they they show they showed
that it was the early treatment group
The Early Tim restricted feeding group
that was more effective than either the
midday Tim restricted feeding group or
the control group at improving insulin
sensitivity which is the key but let's
take a look at some of the the actual
results that came
back so here we're looking at a number
of different topics here and the first
one is a and that's the change in energy
intake when they started this and of
course the control group was Zero
because they didn't change much but you
can see in both the early Tim restricted
feeding group and the midday Tim
restricted feeding group there was a
statistically significant reduction in
the energy
intake and if you want to know more in
terms of the specifics the early
treatment the early Tim restricted
feeding group was a eating period perod
of no more than 8 hours between 6:00 in
the morning and 3:00 in the afternoon
and fasting for the rest of the day
whereas a midday Tim restricted feeding
group was no more than 8 hours between
11:00 in the morning and 8:00 at night
and fasting for the rest of the day and
then of course the control group was
eating whenever they wanted to
eat so once again in the both the early
time restricted feeding and the midday
time-restricted feeding group there was
a statistically significantly
lower amount of energy intake which
means that whenever you restrict eating
it's going to cause a reduction in the
amount of energy intake that's not a
surprise the question is is which one do
you get a better benefit out of now when
they looked at Delta H IR which is a
measure of the insulin sensitivity
notice that there was better sensitivity
there was a reduction in the H air which
is good in the early Tim restricted
feeding group and and not much of a
difference here at all between the
control group and the midday Tim
restricted feeding group now this is
really important to understand a lot of
times studies are done on just Tim
restricted eating but here we're
starting to see that it matters based on
the Circadian rhythm whether or not that
Tim restricted eating is centered around
the morning morning time when circadian
rhythm is designed to have that type of
ingestion of calories or whether it's
later in the evening when it's not uh
let's take a look at the change in the
fasting plasma glucose notice again that
the biggest reduction here was in the
early Tim restricted feeding that that
is not surprising because we know that
the body is more sensitive to insulin in
the morning than it is in the evening
thing as you can see here that the
midday Tim restricted feeding group
really didn't have much of a difference
from the control group so you may be
doing time restricted feeding but if
you're doing it at the wrong time it
doesn't really make a difference let's
look at the change in body weight now
this is really interesting here notice
that despite the fact that there was a
reduction in caloric
intake there was a difference here in
terms of reduction in body weight in the
early Tim restricted feeding group in
other words you could restrict calories
just as well in the midday time
restricted feeding but not see a really
statistically significant difference
what about change in body
fat notice here that the only
statistical significant difference here
was between the early Tim restricted
feeding and the control group okay and
in terms of delta in body fat Mass again
the only statistical significant
difference was that between the early
Tim restricted feeding and the control
group what does all this sort of lead to
that if you're going to do time
restricted eating and limit your intake
of calories to 8 hours a day it's best
to do it earlier in the day when the
circadium rhythm is keyed into that
let's take a look at a couple of other
things here here we see the change in t
necrosis Factor Alpha again the
reduction was statistically significant
only in the early time-restricted
feeding group same for the delta in the
il8 there was a reduction there and also
for a reduction in as which has to do
with uh liver toxicity from
non-alcoholic Ste
steatohepatitis again early Tim
restricted feeding group here we see the
amount of te- cells and we can see that
there was an increase which is is good
again in the early Tim restricted
feeding group that the change in the
diversity of the microbiota of the gut
was higher in the early Tim restricted
feeding group and that the eating
frequency was statistically
significantly Less in the early Tim
restricted feeding and the midday Tim
restricted feeding group but despite
that across the board the measurements
that we wanted to see were either larger
or exclusively seen in the early time
restricted feeding
group again going back looking at
insulin resistance in healthy non-obese
they said that the early time restricted
feeding group showed a larger reduction
in hom IR which is good than either the
midday Tim restricted feeding group or
the control group but there was no
difference between the changes in the
midday Tim restricted feeding and the
control groups
so they say here in the discussion that
the present study has shown that five
weeks of early Tim restricted feeding
but not midday Tim restricted feeding
improves insulin sensitivity reduces
fasting plasma glucose reduces body mass
and adicity ameliorates inflammation and
increases gut microbial diversity
however there was no significant
differences among the three groups with
respect to blood pressure circulating
lipid concentrations hemoglobin
A1c
hscrp which is a inflammatory marker
Sleep Quality or
appetite the study also goes on to say
that the good compliance between the two
protocols in the present study implies
that Tim restricted feeding is an easy
to execute fasting regimen and that the
similar compliance suggests that they
are similarly feasible now realize that
in both groups they were both told to
just eat whatever they wanted to but
limit it to 8 hour days or 8 Hour
periods of time during the day there was
no specific nutritional guidance given
to them and uh what's interesting here
is that there were energy reductions in
both the midday and the early but the
health benefits were seen in just the
early which means that these benefits
were not caused by differences in energy
intake and by the way these findings
showing a benefit of improving insulin
sensitivity there are new numerous
studies which show this this is not a
unique finding and this has been seen
over and over and over again that the
body is most sensitive to insulin in the
morning for instance here is another
article that was published back in
2014 titled dial variation in insulin
sensitivity of glucose metabolism is
associated with dial variations in whole
body and cellular fat acid metabolism in
metabolically normal
women and in the study they measured
plasma and free fatty acid concentration
petate kinetics and skeletal muscle
expression of genes involved in fatty
acid metabolism at breakfast and dinner
in 13 overweight but metabolically
normal
women and what they found was that fatty
acid concentration was 30% greater just
before consuming dinner than breakfast
and that was statistically significant
and remained greater after dinner than
breakfast so therefore they concluded
that metabolically normal women
demonstrate dial variations in fatty
acid metabolism manifested by an
increase in circulating fatty acids
presumably deriv from previous meal
consumption rather than lipolysis or the
breakdown of atopos tissue triglycerides
and a shift in muscle fatty acid
metabolism from oxidation to lipogenesis
these metabolic alter ations could be
responsible for the known evening
decline in insulin sensitivity and
here's the key word that I want you to
see here this is a very well-known even
back in 2014 a known decline in insulin
sensitivity what does this mean this
means that if you are ingesting calories
towards the end of the day it's going to
take more insulin to deal with those
calories and higher amounts of insulin
means insulin resistance which can lead
to all sorts of Downstream effects from
higher levels of
insulin now we've talked about before
and we've shown that infrared light and
red light actually
increases the metabolic activity of the
mitochondria and reduces glucose and so
it's becoming clear and clearer here
that uh that ingesting carbohydrates or
even just calories in general is better
done when the Sun is up and I would even
say more towards the morning based on
the circadium
Rhythm
findings so what can we glean from this
information that we should start to plan
our meals around eating breakfast like a
king lunch like a queen or Prince and
dinner like a popper and the reason is
is because our circadian rhythm is
specifically designed and put in place
to have the enzymes and the substrates
and the pathways primed for dealing with
caloric intake in the morning time as we
can see here the
Delta fasting plasma glucose was lower
when we
had the Tim restricted feeding to the
morning and not into the afternoon or
even into the control
group once again these people with the
EF or the time restricted feeding in the
morning was eating during a period of no
more than 8 hours between 6:00 in the
morning and 3:00 in the afternoon and
fasting for the rest of the day this
means you can drink water but intake no
calories and I can tell you this is
something that I've asked my patients
who have had issues with fatigue issues
with sleeping at night to start to
employ this type of intervention and I
have noticed in my patients uh some
improvements in their symptomatology
specifically in Long covid
patients this may not be for everyone
although notied that in this study there
were very minimal side effects but it's
something that you definitely consider
doing in your life and in lifestyle and
see if this doesn't make a benefit where
we restrict our eating in the evening
time and concentrate more of the intake
of our calories in the morning time now
you may notice that during the first
period of this is done that you're
hungry in the evening it's because your
body is used to eating calories in the
evening time but as you start to get
used to this after about a month or two
you will start to notice that your body
starts to become more attuned and
whereas you might not have been hungry
in the morning to take those calories
your body will be adjusted and ready for
that to Happ happen and whereas you
might have been hungry in the evening
time expecting to have dinner when your
body is used to the fact that it's not
going to have dinner you won't have
those symptoms so don't feel like the
inability to eat or being hungry are
reasons not to employ this technique